This is definitely beyond my expectations.
这完全出乎我的意料之外
Iceland sure is a harsh terrain.
冰岛的地势真的很险峻
There are no trees at all.
一棵树都没有
The sun is so low.
太阳好低
I see now. A country with no fields, huh?
我现在明白了 一个没有原野的国家 是吗?
I guess you can't grow crops when the day is so short.
日照时间这么短 我想你们没办法种植农作物
Because it's winter.
因为现在是冬天
During the summer, the days are actually very long.
到了夏天 白天的时间其实非常长
In areas with the right conditions,
在条件适合的地方
some people grow wheat in the summer.
有些人会在夏天种小麦
But
但是
it's not enough to feed everyone on the island.
收获量不足以供给全国人民
Does everyone on the island
有人在岛上
herd sheep or cattle?
养羊或羊牛吗?
No, there are craftsmen and fishermen too.
没有 有工匠和渔夫
There aren't enough pastures
冰岛没有足够的牧草地
for everyone on the island to raise livestock.
让每个人都能够养牲畜
That's why some people live in communities and fish.
所以有些人会形成部落 以捕鱼为生
That's what Thorfinn's village does.
托尔芬的村落就是这样
Interesting...
是吗...
What do you mean, "interesting"? You were living here, weren't you?
你这是什么意思? 你之前住在这里 不是吗?
Well, it was when I was still a child.
那个时候我还很小
I ran away from home when I was about six.
我大概在六岁那年就离家出走了
From there I spent...
然后我花了...
Um, I spent...
呃...我花了...
Wait, how old am I?
等等 我现在几岁?
Thorfinn, Einar! The village is in sight.
托尔芬、埃纳尔 已经看得到村落咯
Oh man...
我的天...
I'm suddenly really scared.
我突然感到非常害怕
How am I supposed to greet my mother and sister?
我该如何向我妈妈和姐姐打招呼?
Accept your fate, you prodigal son.
接受你的命运吧 你这个浪子
You're finally coming home.
你终于回家了
Okay, good.
好的 很好
- Ouch. - All right.
-唉哟 -好的
Thorfinn.
托尔芬
Everyone in the village is waiting for you.
村里的每个人都在等你
- Who's this? Ylva had a little brother? - I have no clue.
-这是谁?悠瓦有个弟弟? -我完全不知道这件事
- Tell me what my name is. - Huh?
-告诉我 我叫什么名字? -什么?
If you lived here, you should know.
如果你住在这里住过 你就应该知道
F... Faxi?
法克西?
- He got it wrong. - How suspicious. We should tie him up.
-他说错了 -很可疑 我们应该把他绑起来
Come on, go easy on me!
别这样 饶了我吧
It's been so long!
过了太久了
Leif!
雷夫
Oh well. Maybe we should show him to Ylva?
好吧 或许我们该带他去见悠瓦?
That's true.
也是
Ylva was fighting with a merchant from Norway over there.
悠瓦在那里 跟一个来自挪威的商人吵架
Didn't I tell you, Berge?
我不是说过了吗 卑尔根?
Don't you dare try to do shady business in this village.
你竟敢企图在村里做肮脏勾当?
I'm sorry, Ylva.
对不不起 悠瓦
- I'll never do it again. - Huh?
-我再也不敢了 -什么?
What was that? I can't hear you!
那算什么?我听不到
It's fine, Ylva.
没关系啦 悠瓦
I already got my money back.
我已经把钱拿回来了
Hey, Ylva!
喂 悠瓦
I finally brought him back.
我终于把他带回来了
It's Thorfinn.
他是托尔芬
Thorfinn...
托尔芬...
Thorfinn?
托尔芬?
Sister...
姐姐...
Sister!
姐姐
I don't know anyone by that name!
我不认识任何叫托尔芬的人
Come on, Ylva!
别这样 悠瓦
He's Thorfinn, your little brother!
他是托尔芬 你的弟弟
Little brother?
弟弟?
Oh yeah, that was his name.
对喔 他是叫这个名字
My brother died when he was a kid.
我弟弟在小时候就死掉了
But he was alive!
但他还活着
Remember I told you about how I met him in York?
记得我跟你说过 我在约克遇到他的事吗?
Then why didn't you bring him home then?
那你为什么没在那个时候带他回来?
Well, a lot of things happened.
一言难尽 发生了很多事
It was a story you made up to cheer me and my mother up, right?
那是你为了让我和妈妈开心起来 编出来的故事吧?
Thank you, Leif.
谢谢你 雷夫
No, that's not it.
不 不是那样的
More than that...
除此之外...
Huh?
怎么了?
You little midget! What is your motive for tricking Leif, huh?
你这个侏儒 欺骗雷夫 你图的是什么?
- No, no! - You have an excuse?
-不是的! -你有什么借口?
Try telling me!
你说啊!
This is going to be tricky.
情况有点棘手
It's surprisingly difficult to prove that you are yourself.
没想到要证明自己的身份这么困难
Let's go home, Thorfinn.
我们回家吧 托尔芬
If you meet Helga, she'll recognize you.
如果见到海尔加 她就会认出你
Thorfinn...
托尔芬
- Who is that? - That really did a number on him.
-那是谁? -他真的深受打击
It can't be helped, can it?
这也是在所难免 对吧?
Even I almost
就连我也几乎
forgot what my sister and mother looked like.
忘了姐姐和妈妈的样子
It's only natural that they'd forget about me.
她们忘了我也很正常
Who cares if they forgot about you?
她们忘了你又怎样?
You're alive to see your parent
你在外流浪了十年多
after wandering for over a decade.
终于能够回家见父母了
You have to consider it a blessing.
你得把这看做是一种福气
I was separated from my parents when I was a child,
我从小就和父母失散了
and I don't even know where they are.
我根本不知道他们在哪里
I'm envious of you.
我很羡慕你
Want me to act like a dutiful son in your place?
要我代替你做个孝子吗?
No... Sorry, Bug-Eyes.
不用...抱歉 虫眼
Thank you.
谢谢你
Grandma, who is Thorfinn?
外婆 托尔芬是谁?
Thorfinn!
托尔芬
Thorfinn...
托尔芬...
- Mom! - What!
-妈! -什么?
Idiot! Stop making things more confusing!
笨蛋 别再把事情复杂化了
What's the harm?
有什么关系?
No, Helga. This one is...
不是啦 海尔加 这个人是...
Thorfinn...
托尔芬
Mother...
妈妈
You are
你...
all grown up.
长大了
You look just like him.
你跟他就像一个模子刻出来的
You two are father and son after all.
毕竟你们是父子
Mother...
妈妈
I'm sorry...
这一切...
for everything!
我很抱歉
Welcome home,
欢迎你回家
Thorfinn.
托尔芬
Mother! I heard Thorfinn came back!
妈我听说托尔芬回来了
Welcome home, Dad.
爸 欢迎回来
Welcome home.
欢迎回来
Thorfinn?
托尔芬?
Ari...
阿里...
Thorfinn...
托尔芬...
I'm sorry, Thorfinn.
对不起 托尔芬
It's our fault
都是我们的错
that Thors...
托尔兹才会...
Ari, I was the one who was an idiot.
阿里 我才是个笨蛋
All right, then.
好的 那么...
Where are you off to, Einar?
你要去哪里 埃纳尔?
It's about time I leave for the night.
这么晚了 我也该走了
Leif and the crew are staying at Gothi's house,
雷夫和其他伙伴都待在哥提的家
so I'll stay there too.
我也该待在那里
Why don't you stay here?
你就留下来吧
It's a bit small, but we'll manage.
这里虽然有点小 但还是可以的
Oh, but...
但是...
- If you are Thorfinn's brother... - He's my oldest son.
-如果你是托尔芬的兄弟... -他是我的大儿子
- then... - Nice to meet you.
-那么... -很高兴认识你
- you are my son. - Hello.
-你就是我的儿子 -你好
This is your house.
这是你的家
Make yourself at home.
你别拘束
You wouldn't believe, Mother.
妈 你绝对不敢相信
That stingy little merchant changed the price of salt again...
那个吝啬的奸商又偷改了盐的价钱
You're that guy from earlier! How dare you come into my house!
你是之前那个人!你竟敢闯进我家!
Sorry for the intrusion?
不好意思 打扰了
You haven't heard, Ylva?
悠瓦 你还没听说吗?
Is this an inheritance fraud?
你想来诈骗遗产吗?
- Go and target someone who's rich! - So strong!
-去找有钱人吧 -好强壮啊
Ylva, wait.
悠瓦 等等
He's real.
他是真的
Thorfinn actually came back.
托尔芬真的回来了
Real?
真的?
What?
什么?
No way... That can't be.
不可能 绝对不可能
It's not a story Leif made up?
那不是雷夫编出来的故事?
What? It's true?
什么?是真的?
You're the real Thorfinn?
你真的是托尔芬?
I'm home, Sister.
我回来了 姐姐
- Thorfinn! - Sister!
-托尔芬 -姐姐
Where have you been all this time, you fool!
你这个笨蛋 这段时间你跑到哪里去了?
Hey, are you all right, Thorfinn?
你还好吧 托尔芬?
I'm fine, Einar.
我没事 埃纳尔
I am used to being punched...
挨揍我习惯了
One... One punch?
就一拳?
Mom, you're so strong!
妈 你好强壮!
- Mom, you're amazing! - So cool!
-妈 你太厉害了! -太酷了!
Nobody can beat Mom!
没人打得赢我妈
There!
接招!
Come on!
来吧!
Give it momentum!
要有速度感!
That night,
那一晚...
Thorfinn told
托尔芬
his family about what he experienced during
告诉了家人他离家16年来
the 16 years he was away.
所经历的一切
Everything from Thors' death to his departure from Ketil's farm.
从托尔兹之死 到他离开凯特尔的农场
He spoke calmly
他语气淡然
and summarized the important events,
简述重点事件
but his history of hatred and strife,
但他这段充满仇恨和冲突
death and destruction,
死亡和毁灭
despair and regret,
绝望和后悔
and sadness and rebirth
忧伤与重生的经历
left those who were listening speechless.
让在座的各位哑口无言
The people I killed
死在我手上的人
and the slaves who died in despair...
死于绝望的奴隶
They may have had warm families like this themselves.
他们或许也有这么温暖的家庭
My sins are unmeasurable.
我的罪孽无比深重
I have to go
我得离开
and build a land of peace in Vinland.
去文兰打造一个和平之地
Do just that.
你就去吧
Mother?
妈?
There are many people
有很多人
who wish to run away from this world.
想要逃离这个世界
Thors and I
托尔兹和我
ran away from Jomsborg, the land of warriors,
逃离约姆斯伯格这个战士之地
and came to this island.
来到这座岛
People will run away as far as they can
为了逃离战争和奴隶制度
from war and slavery.
大家能跑多远就跑多远
They will run away until they reach a place beyond the horizon.
直到他们跑到一个越过地平线的地方
There, you will be waiting for them in a land of peace you built,
你会在你打造出来的 和平之地等着他们
and you will welcome those people.
欢迎这些人
To do that, you must go.
为了完成这件事 你得离开
Thorfinn, son of Thors.
托尔兹之子托尔芬
Thank you, Mother.
谢谢你 妈妈
Building a nation in Vinland, huh?
在文兰建造一个国家?
That will be a huge project.
会是一个大工程
That's right.
没错
I get that you are determined.
我知道你心意已决
But you'll need manpower, livestock, materials,
但你会需要人手、牲畜、原料
and new ships as well.
和新的船只
First of all, you need funds.
首先 你需要一笔资金
You won't be able to
要募集到
raise such a large sum that easily.
这么大笔的资金 没那么容易
Unless you have my help, that is.
除非你有我帮忙 不然的话...
Thank you, Leif.
谢谢 雷夫
- You're still not going to retire? - You're amazing, Leif.
-你还不打算退休? -你太厉害了 雷夫
- Will it really work out like that? - It'll be fine.
-真的会成功吗? -没事的
No worries. There are many ways to go about it.
别担心 完成这件事的方法有很多
Don't overwork yourself, Dad.
别太逞强了 爸
I'm not overworking.
我没有逞强
You still don't know what I'm capable of.
你仍然不清楚我有多大的能耐
My goodness...
我的天
I can't believe you actually went after him.
我无法相信你真的去追他了
Sister...
姐姐...
I'm sorry.
对不起
Father really was an amazing person.
父亲真的是一个了不起的人
He was strong and kind
他既强壮又仁慈
and always looking far ahead
总是高瞻远瞩
at something I can't perceive.
考量着我不明白的事
After all, he was an "oddball."
毕竟他是个怪咖
Whose grave is this?
这是谁的坟?
A person Father tried to protect a long time ago.
父亲在很久以前试图保护的人
Was it someone important to him?
这个人对他来说很重要吗?
He was a slave.
他是一名奴隶
He ran away from his master
他从主人家逃了出来
and had collapsed outside,
在外面倒地不起
so Father helped him.
所以我爸帮了他一把
He negotiated with the master
他和他的主人商量
and traded eight sheep for the slave.
用八头羊交换了这名奴隶
Eight sheep?
八头羊?
I guess you got your soft heart from your dad.
我想你心肠这么软 就是遗传自你爸
It's freezing! The cold is on another level at night.
好冷哦 到了晚上更是冷得不像话
I'm heading back, Thorfinn.
我要回去了 托尔芬
Hey...
嘿...
if people want to run away from here,
如果有人想逃离这里
where can they go?
他们能逃去哪里?
You know
你知道
the answer, don't you?
答案的吧?
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译:朱未耒